Guide to the Ronald R. Spadafora Papers 1911-2018 (bulk, 1970s-2010s) MS 3134
New-York Historical Society
- Reference ("green book")., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 7434)
  Folder re: Spadafora article on "Atrium Features and Firefighting Tactics" in Fire Engineering (2012). Folder with drafts of chapters for Spadafora green design book; also 3 copies of the book and 4 other books on green design and architecture. A notebook almost entirely empty except for a couple email addresses (related to solar). 4 binders of print matter: firefighter safety/photovoltaic installations (with a CD); Emergency Response to Ethanol Incidents; miscellaneous sustainable design web page print-outs; LEED 2009 rating system for new construction & renovation. Loose articles and other print matter re: microturbines. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference ("green book")., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 7435)
  Folder re: Spadafora's article for WNYF re: wastewater treatment (with floppy and CD). Drafts of green design chapters, with some related emails and permission tables. Folder with print matter re: photovoltaic/solar (with 7 CDs on the topic, looks like codes and "fire ops"). Loose articles and print matter on green/solar/refrigerants/or pollution; some FDNY documents in here, such as AUC 351 (Photovoltaic (Solar Panel) Electrical Systems). Folder of material for Spadafora article in WNYF on wind turbines with CDs and floppy with photos of turbines (including Navy Yard 2010). Materials on green buildings in NYC, especially the Tribeca Green, Visionaire and Solaire all in Battery Park City. Some unlabeled and mixed subject digital materials re: Spadafora presentation on green design at FDIC International conference, 2015. Book on architecture. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference ("green book")., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9069)
  All CDs (some floppies and DVDs). Appears to be a mix of things related to green design, building construction, incidents, etc. Many CDs are unmarked and are likely empty. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference ("green book")., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9827)
  Files with reference material on green matters (building design, firefighting, LEED associate exam prep, etc.). Relates to Spadafora's book, but also a related WNYF article he wrote and talk he gave on the subject. Includes a proposed course syllabus by Spadafora. Several CDs with what appears to be mostly Spadafora's slides/presentations on the topic. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference ("green book")., circa 2011 (Offsite-box 9828)
  2 thick binders of 2011 printouts of the online practice test for the LEED Green Associate exam (green as in environmentally sound). Includes Spadafora's answers, annotations, prep test scores. WWW.greenexamprep.com. by Green Building Education Services.
- Reference ("green book")., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9834)
  Piles of print matter re green construction, design, etc. Print-outs from web, clippings, tearsheets, photocopies, vendor product brochures and catalogs, etc. Presentation on the matter by Spadafora.
- Reference ("green book"). Education., circa 2000s-2018 (Offsite-box 9095)
  Several folders of materials from FDIC (Fire Department Instructors Conference) from about 2008-18. Spadafora presented at one or two on green matters; the box includes several copies of his book, some with tearsheets and other print matter inserted. Various loose print matter re: green design/construction. CDs in the files. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference ("green book"). Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9833)
  Files for book: book proposal, outline, permissions, emails on admin matters, drafts, reference material (tearsheets, clippings, a couple pieces of building material). Also includes files on other green issues, especially ethanol and biodiesel fuel use for fire engines.
- Reference ("green book"). Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9857)
  Print matter: 13 books on green buildings. Videocassette on "Building Green: Audubon House." 2 binders on international green construction code, 2010. Artifacts: elaborate compass from Asia (or at least Asian characters), Spadafora conference speaker ID. (Includes artifacts, video)
- Reference ("green book"). Specifics (South Africa)., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9145)
  Binder of print material re: ESS (energy storage systems). CDs re: wind turbines, photovoltaics, fire code revision article, fires in hgh rises, etc. USB flash drive labeled "Africa." Folder re: range hood duct cleaning. Folders on various Spadafora articles: fuel cells, green energy/ESS, most with CDs. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference. Policies & Procedures., circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 9786)
  All print matter, bulk of which relates to hazardous material. Most of this is general texts on hazmat, much specifically in context of first responder guidebooks. One binder labeled "Right to Know" includes photocopies of "material safety data sheets (MSDS)." Some of the materials are FDNY products, including a "Hazard Action Guide", a glossy booklet on "FDNY: Hazmat", "Exposure Control Plan," "All Units Circular 278R: Infection Control Program." There is a text and some other print matter on fire suppression and foam.
- Reference. Personal, circa 1970s-2009 (Offsite-box 9556)
  Print matter, mostly, related to arson and fire investigations, and also fire safety/prevention. NYC-specific: FDNY Bureau of Fire Investigation annual reports for 2005-2009; laminated cards FDNY vital statistics CY 2009; Executive Report: Fire Safety Outreach Campaigns in High Risk Communities, July 2005-Feb 2006; "Arson in New York, 1984" report by Mayor Koch's Arson Strike Force, 1985; Division of Fire Investigation (DFI) training bulletins & circulars, ca 1978-80; "Predicting Arson Risk in New York City: A First Report" (1980) and "Manpower Needs for the Investigation of Arson in New York City" (1979), both by Arson Strike Forces; Executive Summary update on the Red Cap Program (anti-arson), circa 1982. Other material is general reference: arson clippings, photocopies of articles, booklets from organizations (Insurance Committee for Arson Control, US Dept of Commerce, Fire Prevention K-3 curriculum from Rochester FD, FBI/Bomb scene Investigation, International Fire Service Training Association/1st edition of Fire Cause Determination; and many small pamphlets on subject), mostly from the 1970s-80s, with some into the 1990s. Spadafora's notebook from fire marshal training school (Oct-Nov 1984), and fire marshal study material and exam questions from late 1970s-mid 80s.
- Reference. Personal. (Offsite-box 9805)
  Print matter: Overstuffed file of material re: "lightweight building construction." FDNY print: annual reports, medal day, laminated vital stats, "runs and workers." Print matter from NYS and texts re: fire protection and prevention. 2 unrelated books re: Al Qaeda. Artifacts: certificate of appreciation plaque to Spadafora; various Spadafora ID cards. Booklet from Brooklyn Ave School thanking Spadafora for coming to the school. NY drivers manual and related. (Includes artifacts)
- Reference. Personal., circa 1999-2015 (Offsite-box 9841)
  10 copies of Spadafora's Fire Protection book (2015). 6 books on building design or fire protection. Proceedings of international conference on fire service deployment analysis, 1999. Homeland security report on abandoned cold storage warehouse multi-firefIghter fatality fire, Worcester, Mass, 1999. Packet re: Spadafora contracting with company to produce a video for firefighting exam prep (2010).
- Reference. Personal., circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9865)
  Spadafora's Fire Science 101 course outlines, reading material, etc. Spadafora's student notebook on hydraulics class (1985). Print matter: Texts on firefighting hydraulics (9), chem-bio handbooks (3), general fire/firefighters (2). Pack of brochures re: fire safety & prevention, sprinklers, extinguishers. DVD on fire & hazard control. Artifacts: sprinkler heads. (Includes digital formats, artifacts)
- Reference. Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 13864)
  Files for Spadafora's articles on saw tooth roofs, lofts, and and mill lofts. Print matter, drafts, version of firefighting procedures. Lots of CDs, likely photos and/or drafts. Certificate of thanks to Spadafora from Burn Center. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference. Personal., circa 1947-2016 (Offsite-box 13865)
  Print matter. Emergency Response Guidebook, 2012. Various anniversary booklets: Columbia Association 81st; FDNY 150th; Asian-American Council 31st; Chiefs Association 100th; Engine 8 150th; Ladder 20 125th; 1966 23rd street fire 50th and earlier. FDNY Foundation Dinner awards, 2016. Technical material: NYC Citywide Incident Management System manual, 2005; "Practical approaches to Firefighting", 1985; Great American Insurance reprint on construction; 2 copies of Popular Science, Jan 1947, with fire engines and article; children's book on firemen (1950s); binder of articles on fire fatalities (Hackensack and Charleston). Spadafora's personal "Probationary FF Notebook, 9/2/78-10/6/78." CDs: 23rd St Memorial, FDNY War Years 2, New York Fire College history, FDNY class of 1978 30th reunion. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference. Personal., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 13871)
  Copies of Spadafora book "Fire Protection Equipment and Systems" part of "Brady Fire Series," published by Pearson, 2015, some with inserts. Rest of material in box appears to be reference material related to parts of the book. Folder of documents re: administration for the book (outline, emails, etc.). Binder of peer book reviewer comments, etc. Binder: Explosion Protection Solutions from vendor Fike. Binder: dust hazard study from Fed agency, 2006. Binder: OSHA Fire Service Features, 2015.
- Reference. Personal. Policies & Procedures., circa 2000s-2017 (Offsite-box 13872)
  Print matter: Binder: ANSI/SPRI RP-14 standard re: wind design for vegetative roofing system (green roof systems). Binder: print matter of various forms re: solar photovoltaic systems. Binder: Firefighter Safety & Emergency Response for Solar Power Systems, 2010. Binder: Bridging the Gap: Fire Safety & Green Buildings, 2010. Packet for Spadafora, course FIS 202 at John Jay (Fire Protection Systems), includes syllabus and copies of reading articles. Files on carbon dioxide, argon, inergen, and other such chemicals, probably re: book. Loose FDNY Department orders and Bureau of Operations memos, 2017.
- Reference. Specifics (WNYF article incidents), circa 1941-2005 (Offsite-box 9800)
  Old WNYFs starting about 1941 and ending about 1969, then 1986-88, then 2002-07 (probably gaps; didn't see 1970s & 1990s here). Packets on Spadafora's 1989 WNYF article "Preventing a Next Time," 2005 WYNF "Command Continuity" article, and other article notes/drafts/related material. 2 packs of snapshots: 2000 Valentine Ave apartment building; unidentified building (1998).
- Reference. World Trade Center., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9774)
  Appears to be all reference materials related to fire prevention/suppression (articles, tearsheets, web page printouts, Powerpoint printouts, vendor product procedures, etc.). Generally appears to be concepts/science/products, not incident/NYC specific. Half of box has individually foldered articles. Rest of box is a loose mass of documents. Some CDs and DVDs on same topic. Not related: many copies of small laminated card "From Lockerbie 12/21/88 to New York 9/11/01" with little or no obvious tie to a particular course. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference. World Trade Center., circa 2002-2012 (Offsite-box 9886)
  Several folders of reference material (tearsheets, procedures, product descriptions, webpages, CDs) on classes of fires and related suppression/extinguisher systems/agents, and also related firefighting apparatus/tools and air systems, 2005-12. Appears to be used in connection with his classes and writings. Only WTC material here is a binder of articles from Plumbing Engineer magazine, 2002-05; the articles are by Richard B. Schulte writing for the "Fire Protection" column; not all his columns are on WTC (generally on high rises/fire safety) but many of these are; with a CD "One Meridien Plaza" and "11/15/2010 Shanghai China high rise fire." (Includes digital formats)
- Reference. World Trade Center. Personal., circa 1990s-2010s (Offsite-box 9755)
  Print matter: 6 textbooks, mostly math. Binder of instructions on how to use St Joseph's College Blackboard system (2005). Packet of material related to Durham, NC Fire Dept awards ceremony that Spadafora went to (2010). Some loose clippings & papers related to post-9/11 matters (WTC), including tiff with Giuliani. Some kind of report/article by Spadafora with somebody's commentary. One firefighting book. 1 equipment catalog. A CD labeled as "with the files for Ron's book." About 30 floppies, most labeled, though somewhat obscurely. Some on fire science, but not all obviously so. (Includes digital formats)
- Specifics (Roosevelt Island tram). Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1965-2016 (Offsite-box 9542)
  Print matter: FDNY Rescue Operations Strategic Plan 2014-16; Roosevelt Island Tram emergency rescue plan 2011. FEMA Wide Area Search Participant Manual 2013. Textbooks on vehicle rescue, confined spaces handbook, "The Rescue Company" inscribed to Spadafora by author Ray Downey, fire prevention, Army firefighting (1965).
- Specifics (Brooklyn fire marshal reports). Personal. Reference., circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9900)
  Print matter: Several folders of individual articles on fire investigations (general, not particular ones) as well as tearsheets and books on arson and related. Photocopies of Spadafora's Bureau of Investigations Fire Reports (Fire Marshal reports): from Brooklyn 12/9/1984-4/27/1986. Paystubs, ID, and a few other documents related to Spadafora's teaching position at John Jay College.
- Specifics (Building Code Task Force). World Trade Center., circa 2002-2004 (Offsite-box 7431)
  Folders of working files etc re: WTC Building Code Task force (leading to WTC/Skyscraper Safety Bill, 2004); some CDs with related Powerpoints. Also files and print matter on the NYC Model Building Code task force, 2004, with CDs related to the International Building Code including a IBC/BCCNY comparison. See also box 7430. (Includes digital formats)
- Specifics (Building Code Task Force). World Trade Center. Education., circa 2002-2006 (Offsite-box 7430)
  Spadafora was on the NYC Model Buildings Code Program, Fire Protection Technical Committee (circa 2003-04). Box includes much material related to this: Binder of material from Alliance for Fire Safety re: A Call to Action: Why & How the New Model Building Codes Should be Changed (2003); Binder with table comparing 2003 International Building Code (IBC) with 2002 NYC Building Code (BCCNY); International Fire Code print matter; thick folder of minutes, email, reports, etc. Also a thick folder on the World Trade Center Building Code Task Force, 2004, which seems related but not the same as above (includes Spadafora's article in WNYF on this, with floppies). Some material on FDNY training for new fire code (2006). CD for Fire Inspection Resource Exercise Simulation (training). See also box 7431. (Includes digital formats)
- Specifics (Fire Department High School). Education. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9893)
  Includes several files concerning FDNY initiatives to develop new forms of training for firefighters (distance learning/web-based, CDs, partnerships with NYU or other colleges, vendor software for computer-based training from ATR Inc and others, and the like). Also includes extensive material on "FDHS" (a/k/a Homeland Security High School), a high school setting in Fort Totten, targeted at Thomas Jefferson High School students from East New York, with rich planning and execution documentation (2003-06) (idea is to create apprentice firefighters, as part of a larger goal of increasing diversity in recruitment and ranks). Copy of Columbia University's report "Improving Workforce Diversity in the FDNY", 2004, with two earlier draft reports (2003); research done by School of International and Public Affairs for FDNY. Several Spadafora business cards. CDs of "Battalion Chiefs Digital Imaging and Presentation Training" and DVD "Powerpoint Presentation: Critique Notes/Digital Photos" both from 2005. Copies of Powerpoint slides and other material on "Personal Safety System." (Includes digital formats)
- Specifics (fire prevention inspection form revision), circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 9878)
  All relates to fire prevention inspection forms, specifically in context of a 2005 revision of the checklist and guide in response to the 2003 death of a firefighter (Spadafora was on revision project team). Documents include folders of old forms and related procedures; folder of new forms; related roll-out info: several copies of 2005 AFID Building inspection training instructor's manual, several copies of the final (and draft) Inspection Forms Reference Manual; VHS video: "Fire Prevention Inspection Form Redesign Project" running 6:26; 2 DVDs of an Introduction to the new AFID Inspection Forms and Reference Book (July 2005); many floppies of Powerpoint slides and apparently copies of drafts and final of the forms and reference manual. (Includes digital formats, video)
- Specifics (Fire prevention inspections), circa 1964-2006 (Offsite-box 9898)
  All material re: fire prevention inspections/procedures. Notice of Violation (NOV) Manual (1991). AFID Building Inspection Forms-Curriculum, Instructors Manual (2005), Spadafora identified in acknowledgements as Assistant Chief of Training in the Bureau of Training/Office of Fire & Life Safety. Field Activity Report manual (2002), includes forms, codes, procedures, and related. Manual for inspecting places of worship/religious structures. Copies of Powerpoint slides re: Regulatory Reform (Fire safety) Order 2004, with attached memo re: fire door requirements of April 2006. Outlines of instructions for completing various inspection forms. Booklet of blank "Vacate" forms (Violation Order Book), with Do Not Enter stickers in English and Spanish (1988). Binder of photocopies of various FDNY forms. "Manual for Fire Protection" booklet issued by the Division of Training (1964). NYC Fire Prevention Code, Chapt 19, with heavily annotated training course (fire tech/fire promotion) material, circa 1974-1980, with some mid-80s. Copy of NYC Reference Standard (RS) 19 re: safety of public and property during construction operations, 1990s. Binder of copies of slides: "AFID-Battalion Chief Response, Fire & Life Safety", 2002, with overviews of requirements etc re: pyrotechnics, vacate situations, construction, etc. (See also box 9548)
- Specifics (firefighter fatalities). Education. Reference., circa 1980s-2010s (Offsite-box 9209)
  Binder of safety tips (1980s). Safety & Inspection Services Command: about 10 investigation reports into fatalities or serious injuries of firefighters (2000s). Print matter re: FF Professional development. Print matter re: communications/radio codes, 911/response system. Staying Alive seminar. 4 training CDs. Field Operations pocket guide for NYC urban area. (Includes digital formats)
- Specifics (firefighter fatalities). Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 2000s-2012 (Offsite-box 9091)
  About 8 investigation reports & related matter for fatalities (2000s). Binder labeled "Safety/Health" tearsheets, etc on aspects, including FDNY suicide awareness campaign documents (2012). Very overstuffed binder labeled "Communications Manual": tearsheets, bulletins, etc. re: 911 (emergency call number), response times, procedures, etc. print matter.
- Specifics (Hurricane Katrina). Personal., circa 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 9896)
  Bulk are materials re: Katrina/New Orleans: photos of Spadafora; tearsheets/clippings/WNYF article/other print matter; "Fed Response: Lessons Learned"; memo "FDNY after action review of the New Orleans deployment (2005); memo "Second deployment" by Spadafora and Robert Sweeney (they were sent to relieve first deployment starting Sept 15, 2005); Spadafora's after-action report (Oct 2005); certificate of appreciation to Spadafora; binder of Spadafora notes, blank forms, and info; incident action plans and other related plans for Holy Cross complex; several other documents related to FDNY Hurricane Katrina Relief Task Force; status reports (Sept 2005); several scrunched up and folded oversize maps and other images re: New Orleans matter. Artifacts: Spadafora's Unified Katrina Command ID badge, Mardi Gras beads, sealed packet of food in containers, a few incident management pins. Small packet of documents (travel-related and snapshots) re: Spadafora presentation in Montana (2003). (Includes artifacts)
- Specifics (Hurricane Sandy, Hurricane Katrina). Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 13861)
  Materials for Spadafora's article in WNYF re: Hurricane Sandy (a/k/a Superstorm Sandy), including CD of Powerpoint, FDNY's and NYC's After Action Reports; Fire Engineering special issues, some miscellaneous related articles and docs, floppy, some unrelated? CDs ("crane" and "high water vehicle"). About 110 CDs (maybe some DVDs): some FDNY training but most appear to be photos for Spadafora's green book, from Sandy, from uncertain context (lofts, buildings, cast iron, etc.), about 10 from Katrina and Rita in New Orleans, some Powerpoints (2000s). Some unused blue exam books from John Jay. (Includes digital formats)
- Specifics (loft building fires). Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9825)
  Print matter: 12 books on building construction/architecture. NYC building maintenance code. Some photocopies of articles. All seems to relate to Spadafora drafting a Firefighting Procedure for Loft Building fires: there are drafts and multiple copies of this procedure. See also box 9826.
- Specifics (loft building fires). Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9826)
  Almost all material related to building construction methods and materials, including text books, codes, articles, most specifically in context of firefighting. Much of this appears to be in the context of loft buildings and specifically for a 2006 article in WNYF on the subject written by Spadafora (loft fire procedures (2 binders), WNYF issue from 2006 with Spadafora article on loft fires, original snapshots for article, Spadafora's typed version of article). Material on the subject extends past 2006 article to 2008 and later. Box also holds National Fire Academy's "Instructional Techiques for Company officers" instructor & student guides (binder). See also box 9825.
- Specifics (Republican Party National Convention, 2004). Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9853)
  Articles by Spadafora in WNYF (2) on origin of IMT, has CD and related materials. Materials on shadow team to Montana for the Robert Fire/training on incident management. Print matter: several handbooks on IMT (search & rescue, national interagency mobilization, escape routes, etc.) Blank log book for incident events. Videocassette from US DOJ re: "Surviving the Secondary Device". Citywide Incident Management System (CIMS) training (sign-up, Powerpoint slides, etc.). FDNY terrorism & disaster preparedness strategy, 2007. Material on FEMA's National Incident Management System. 2004 Republican National Convention Operational Plan. (Includes digital formats, video)
- Specifics (Republican Party National Convention, 2004). Policies & Procedures. World Trade Center. Reference., circa 1980s-2000s (Offsite-box 9554)